for over a hundred years Britain's
mentally ill were hidden from society
fast Victorian simes
those who are locked away have left
their own
testimony remember getting the first
glimpse at the hospital
big rule in place in the clock tower in
on that and I remember then thinking
my goodness la maleta myself a often
in the last decades in the Asylum's
psychiatrist tried to Kenya as well as
care for patients some other attempts
will Bobak food is also
me the holes call went as the brew
michael is a bit knows that this was a
time when treatment was undergoing a
revolution
some patients felt science was being
pushed too far
districts say probe on
and then peace map right now
these institutions had to be shut down
when it happened
it was a moment in history that changed
Britain's
this is the story of the closing at the
Asylum's the often troubled lives they
left behind
high Royds in Yorkshire was typical of
the greatest silence
it was a village in its own right with
it informs
a butcher a bakery even a railway
station ran right to the center the
Assign
at its height did held over 2,500
patients
it was just much you can't walk around
all day and and never walk round all
love it
the new I was in a place with the
longest career tools I've ever seen the
movie with modules with Corey Deuel
ok a lot
patients were socially inadequate not
strictly speaking and mentally ill not
tested by she's not
suffering from delusions nom showing any
thought disorders at all
simply inadequate and couldn't cope
there were mounted
ok
knows could burgers a region Bradford
who tempest patient in here
would certainly have thought that they
were doing the right thing by the
patient I'll really they were doing the
right thing by their towns
I think that would build
hit an awful word isn't it great you you
could
think and think Rackley their to
patients with don't hear
by their relatives by the community they
weren't wanted
and higher wages a convenient place for
their
it was not just high rides
many Britons asylums contained patients
who had been locked up for new clear
psychiatric reason
people coach admit it on all sorts at
UPS Ground
victim didn't really have anything
directly to do with their
mental states and their families had
abandoned them in there was no one to
one
to support them outside the institutions
even in the nineteen fifties some
patients ended up in the Asylum's
for a very long time this patient used
to be a skill Gardiner
he came here thirty five years ago and
he has no soda
he fought in the 14-18 wall many
patients were admitted on genuine
medical grounds
something easily treatable outside
hospital nowadays
Agnes ibn heavy chains mystifies me
have on a having open in shape anyway I
just play it
name
after the war the gym Tugwell had left
the army and was suffering genuine
mental distress
she was 25
living with her foster parents panic
attacks were making her life
a misery I wanted a right now
and I felt like Pinkberry sockets
baby handsome a company that operated
Saint John's hospital near a man's body
was Jones local asylum
to her family it seemed to offer some
hope of refuge
she was deeply committed to Cal my man
asked about
Irene he gave up on Wed
good action to help can be don't see
I agent had bad tho he bet you one bill
Nagy
sell your capital One Bank was damaged
by the next page
up that way and next time down here and
then the next from happening
say that it would be willing to one in
every three Champlain Hideki the
indicated
living at my 3G man
who
it was to be the start of a surge in a
century inside mental hospitals for Jen
the new in the early fifties the regime
was harsh
some others she met were not what she
would have thought of
has made you with money
is there were however minute nothing
wrong with them about me
I don't think much wrong with me the
asylum life was empty and repetitive
ok
after months on her ward Joan arsonist
if she could help with the beds
it was a wave occupying herself for a
part of the day
I asked about that but the bay average
tenia mucho maintenance sixty-page a
evening to hang veribanc made all the
base
alcohol confident escape from her
feelings of anxiety
one evening in the asylum Joan potholed
have some spirits
and ended up drunk and in the wrong
world
I suppose to and find everything K
raking in
take the chill this down and have passed
separate challenge 10
when I came in averaging effective sale
their factories but
you get him in a current he up
every hill where and you have tamraz
night vision had this blanket if he
shared it a little better he ate
despite the vast majority of patients
having committed no offence
life in the silence was dominated by
security the words were not open
the doors were opened may do it was open
to let the patient out and then close
after he got
Hulu
closeted prison the atmosphere the the
room the
dry mu commits euro patient
mysteries keep in many ways the largest
island still housed innate
rather than patients conditions inside
her daughter little in the last half
century
the change was on its way what
this leaflet
is coming through your letterbox one day
soon read it
calf when the labor government created
the National Health Service in 1948
mental institutions were entirely
separate from general hospitals
you'd before the NHS was created there
was some debate as to whether or not
the Asylum's country would be included
in the National Health Service
and it was decided finally did it would
be included
and by including it I think it did
helped to
to bring the systems together hospitals
specialist services
medicines it was the parting of ways
with the old pool
etiology national a dementia patient was
being embraced by
the NHS a sauce the whole idea from the
quality of membership
while medical science has advanced
rapidly in the years before the creation
of the NHS
therapy for mental illness was still
very limited
but now psychiatrists began to
experiment with new ideas
and new treatments you get an increasing
view that mental illness is really the
same as other physical illnesses and can
be treated using the same sort it means
using physical interventions that work
on the body
one of these relatively new treatments
was the controversial
electroconvulsive therapy or ECT
it meant putting an electrical current
through the brain to induce a seizure
it seems ease the symptoms are severe
depression in some patients
though psychiatrists could not explain
how it worked
Boulevard here in here
and then research and then your carried
your face
have epileptic fit whole
ECT units were set up so that patients
can be treated in large numbers
until the early nineteen fifties the
procedure was carried out largely
without
anesthetic a member of staff would lean
heavily on the need another one at the
ankles and on
at each side hole in the shoulders down
and the consultant
applied electrical charge through the
brain the patient of course jerked very
very
Thailand leak that's why we were holding
him down
because it had been known that this
pretty you could cause crashes and had
cartridges
ok despite appearances
ECT was regarded as a step forward it
seemed to offer some patients a real
hope for improvement
your insulin doses
are being prepared and checked another
the so-called shock treatments was
incident therapy where doctors induced
coma by injecting large doses of insulin
into the body insulin coma treatment to
give it its full title
offers the greatest likelihood of relief
and Kira
ha some patients whose illness is a
deep-seated nature
she said H&amp;M yeah
at 10 I have a nice to have you seven
patients J
carol Wright injure homemade they would
speaking of which I have been
actually it made him feel Priya it would
burn a Polish should be a
in that body and drop the blood sugar
level very very low
and to into coma and that was supposed
to be
beneficial and some way to the brain in
this condition
the mine has a chance to be completely
relaxed and the functions of the brain
have the opportunity
are as it were setting out on a new
power when consciousness returns
physical treatments like this advance
the image of psychiatry as a faster than
typing scientific branch of medicine
in reality insulin proved
harmful medical failure forty-four
people were killed from its affects
during this period
may be bad Neeb effect and I had
January we can't give you any more
incident this is affecting you baby have
a pic
but one former treatment was more
drastic than all the others
the lobotomy
some psychiatrists believe that by
removing sections of the brain itself
certain serious mental disorders could
be permanently treated
at least 15,000 these operations known
as prefrontal economies
were performed in Britain leaders also
it was a blind operation me the holes
Cole
who wish those who called room rent is
the Bruin
the way with a bit was it those new
until much much legal any attempt to
refine the sexy where the cut through
the
those lots of patience walking around
with two holes in FP the side of the
forehead
that you could see the actual didn't
wear this skull had been there
to pound away and an instrument had been
put in
11 is it had been that hasn't been left
alone
I heard them misfortune came over in a
min
in all sixty whom sixty
patience who had the operation
and the go through
the one of them was a little
health treasure do
personal to change towards the end of
the nineteen fifties
this crude form of prefrontal equal to
me was phased out
little was then known about the workings
of the brain for most patients there was
no alternative to long periods in an
asylum
they will voluble people and the public
wasn't interested it could be a recipe
for abuse
David McCarthy began his career as a
psychiatric nurse
in 1957 at san Nicolas hospital near
Newcastle
he was shocked by the treatment
routinely handed out to long-stay
patients
the first time was on the first day on
the 1st ward
and I worked on well and the charge
nurse that was showing me around
smacked a no or little old blind man
across the back of the head
so fiercely that the flu across the room
unhittable
I was very shocked because
the charge nurse had been quite nice to
me when I came on the ward
and hand 100 I was a bit lost for words
and he said
dem don't you know if you live along
shit you become shared
theme this kinda brutality was
considered almost inevitable for some
other categories at the many ppl
on the ward for a difficult patient
dimick's colleagues called the stuff for
page
some therapy the patient had been
I'm active rather histrionic Lee sliding
office chair
onto the floor and this was during the
the unofficial stop breast time at
dinner time
potentially the charge nurse at the
world
got sick at tennis disappeared into the
target area
he came out with the numbers look good
for the cold water
I'm through it
moreover the patient in the dayroom mom
everyone to see
that alarmed about that over the top in
the patient's head
and within a few seconds a patient and
slid back on the floor again
so he called a staff nurse and they
dragged in by scholar
crossed low into the bathroom area the
latest shouted from me
and I went in and they were holding him
under
the water in the bath bring them up
and pushing under
when they stopped Derek had to drive the
patient of
I wanted to charge nurse who is in the
office and said
is completely dry down to put new
clothes on and
can I have the key to get the shocks in
issue centered
and he said to me what do you think this
is
brooklyn's send him out has he is
there was no evidence have this kind of
treatment at high rates but
investigations in subsequent decades
revealed persistent abuse
other side limbs I'm convinced it was
endemic and in fact
enquiries later on proved at the same
things were going on
in other male cites a mental hospitals
right throughout the country
by the mid-nineteen fifties
almost home of the New NHS's beds were
given over to mental illness
or mental disability and the cost was
mounting
hope came from Liberty Reserve
scientists working on a new generation
of drugs
French psychiatrist started to use a
drug called cruel primacy
which proved to be very effective in
calming psychotic patients
within a few years log Axtell
as it came to be called here had spread
right across Europe and America
it was the first in a new range drugs an
important
the will to revolutionize the way mental
illness could be treated
these drugs promised ended the lock
doors anime boys
and ultimately ended the asylum system
itself
it was quite exciting
you know this was something new and we
ask you wouldn't know it is really hard
to get involved in it
it was a turning point
some psychiatrists felt that the new
drugs had solved the riddle a mental
illness
trouble losing the this into the pros
others hey you as well
unbearable which it isn't booked till
your optimism is quite important
produced
so Kairos will euros
the new spirit of optimism was felt
keenly and highlights
doctors here became pioneers at the new
drugs research
much to the benefit to the silence green
in each
in Chad pity
formidable reputation you know in the
same state
he too is run in some respects like a
fishing and there was a keen desire
in the early fifties to change its image
for the better doctor Roy Hollins
started his career
as a biochemist he was invited to higher
rates and given his and stuff to
research the effective the truck lithium
on the brain chemistry patients I want
to do
time came in from work on patients on
and manic-depressive the nation's mine
got some useful results
who your ID laws tune
to Obama's work went into the patient
and measure what came out doctor Hollins
research proved a vital step in
establishing lithium
as one of the most prominent need ranks
it is still widely used today
as a treatment
arrange new drugs ING's during the
nineteen fifties and sixties
but they're not just new there is a
whole new idea about them in a new idea
is that they all specific treatments for
specific disorders
said that rather than just being
substances that drug people contain
people said eight people
which is what was thought about the old
drugs they all seem to be substances
that somehow
work on the underlying physical basis of
mental disorder
it may have looked and felt like an old
Victorian asylum
but I really it was now at the forefront
to the drugs revolution
it was acknowledged as a research center
for mental illness
and its medical staff presented their
findings all over the world
the new wonder drugs
created hope for the future but even
before they arrived some enlightened
psychiatrists
had started to develop a more humane
approach to cams
the first thing we do
a powerful improving the new moving
and the decorations who plays
walls to time occupation
I'll
they were killed principal
the employment news:
the evil the num said the advances in
treatment
some patients were now being given a new
program that activity
of I'll
healing is the hallmark the hospital
these handcrafted one for money
a piece of homemade car or basket these
approved to these ladies
that they can still do some things as
well as anybody and even if the work is
slow and clumsy
it's better than berudi occupational
therapy this is called
it serious scientific treatment but more
fundamental reforms were taking place
the first hospitals for now starting to
experiment with an
open-door policy something that would
have once been anathema to the ethos
of the asylum at one time
patients had nothing to do except to
walk around inside
and cokes now when the first things I
did was just sold on the ratings
there is news to a candle supports
to you that people come and go much from
3d
did the signs just physically was spruce
top
game declaration made more homely
in the mid-nineteen fifties there were
over a hundred and fifty thousand
patients
mental hospitals more than at any time
in history
politicians from all parties agreed that
the asylum regime was very expensive its
morality was now
also being questioned in 1959 the
Conservative government passed a radical
new
active parliament introduced a more
compassionate approach to the treatment
of the mentally
in perhaps one of our greatest reforms
is in the new Mental Health Act which
interprets in modern terms
a new approach to mental sickness so
that it is no longer on illness with the
stigma
but one which should be treated with the
same sympathy
and understanding as any Obama physical
disability
the nation's conscience have been
pricked
Britain was coming face to face with its
asylums
which had quarantine the mentally ill
from society for over a hundred use
you had to justify not locking the doors
but why you locking the doors
it was that I wasn't accepted that you
simply love and that what he always done
why a locking them why do these patients
have to be locked in
the nineteen
59 act represented
the final break with the Victorian
period
to mister cheney point because it
recognized
for the first time that Jim the mental
hospital
and in the future was not necessarily
going to be the main
lockerz have cash for people with mental
health problems
the impetus for change was gaining
strength
but it took a maverick politician to
grasp the vision of a nation without
asylums enough panel shattered the sense
that the
old mental institutions were shameful
relics of the past
in a prophetic speech in 1961
he made a dramatic pledge to tear them
down
mud I'm
now look and see what are the
implications of these bold words
0 they imply nothing less than the
elimination up by far the greater part
of this country's mental hospitals
as they exist today 0
%uh
it was a call to arms and Powell was
under no illusions about the strength of
the likely opposition to his plans
huh
there they stand isolated majestic
imperious brooded over by the gigantic
water tower
and chimney combined rising unmistakable
and daunting out to the countryside
the asylum switch our forefathers build
with such immense solidity
to express the nation's day 0
do not for a moment underestimate powers
a resistance
to holler sold homes mom
the water tower became the defining
images speech
I'll enough power was determined to
remove everything it stood for
and replace it with a new model of care
based in the units have general
hospitals
and community I'll p.m. for told the end
the mental hospital regimes at that time
they wear
100 or so in this country in not had
closed
none of them had any tension closing at
that time
so this was a visionary speech the
church with looking beyond
the current regime to a completely
different
social landscape in it was a national
social conscience that was awakened
and it was beginning of the end for
places like this
enough power had to note that both new
plan to mental health
outside the SI rims that as he predicted
it had little immediate impact on the
echoing words and endless corridors
Britain's existing mental hospitals the
new here
altering the brain's chemical balance
remain focus
the new drugs which had initially held
out the promise of closing yes I did
now seemed to be doing the opposite in
the nineteen sixties there was a growing
recognition that drugs might not be
ending the asylum culture but prolonging
it
the
a BBC documentary in 1969 found the
conditions with in mental hospitals
was still disturbing ok
the
for many patients the tranquilizing
drugs well causing new problems
ok they are basically sedative drugs but
they produce a very special sorted
sedation
which is a bit like having parkinson's
disease so that not only did they sedate
she but they make you physically
rigid and they they physically slow you
are and the men case very well
to me or like the system came down on me
so
heavily straightaway was just
do you know as if things like dogs in
shock treatment was the answer to my own
happiness or whatever
which it certainly wasn't it made things
a lot worse
jeanne davison was brought up in a
working-class district to Bradford
at the end of the fifties
very much expected me that I leave
school and go to work in a factory are
some kind of data in Joplin at
that firm was difficult because I found
it bother him
in her teens she began to feel depressed
and alienated
I was dissatisfied with my lifestyle
and I suppose that in a way last the
stock to be
they felt a feeling that I got that life
was empty and meaningless
gene felt that she needed someone to
talk to
she lost her GP
for an appointment with a psychiatrist
who recommended that she spent the week
addressed an observation
highlights her local mental hospital
right back from childhood
so joked with all the kids saying will
take it away in a green BAM for higher
energy know it was the
mental hospital that we all knew about
the
from
lot comes out in my mind was walk you
know
the dry and getting the first glimpse at
the hospital
in the thought of a BMI I think that
made it look maybe
mom got they feel whatever the big
looming play through the clock tower and
a and I remember than thinking
my goodness what a mother and myself in
power
Jean arrived on award when medical
confidence in the positive effects of
drugs
was at its height %uh morning after she
arrived she was given
first taste blog acton
no wonder it not me out made me drowsy
because that's what ya got told those
it's a really strong
what the call anti-psychotic drug
while heavily drugged jeanne was
persuaded to sign up to a course have an
extra convulsive therapy
ECT was routinely being carried out with
anesthetic
but the procedure was still terrifying
three teenagers
who'd had no previous contact with
psychiatry
pick up any breakfast that morning on
a small ambulance comes and picks up all
the patients on the way
and took me to another part of the
building where the DC ten
given an injection in a damn
this to dry you now apparently an
top she swallowing you tom was one says
when you have in effect
our ass scared yet I mean I'm even
scared and just up in an anesthetic from
stop them and the file
electric shocks going in tea brain the
came out with a hot water bottle
and where to put it on the back about a
month about move aimed found out for the
anesthetic injection
and I remember feeling really powerless
lead amid
back I mean this injection panicked and
wanted it all to stop by and try to
a fight them to stop them doing it then
and
good
and then the next thing I remember is
I'm wakey not been really come field
feel really disorientated its light
everything
familiar but not quite right thumb I'll
and the worst thing though I found was
he told that they might be tempting
effects lot not but I
saw what if what he's doing some
permanent damage
to the brain this this that was horrible
the
what was initially supposed to be a week
observations gene
became stay have several months on an
inpatient ward time rides
ok this turned into five years today
patient
by the end 18th out at the hospital
itself had become part of the problem
not the solution I fell up just got
soaked in
to going along with their noms Oh
whatever you known
it's strange really is like a
yeah a different world that use OnStar
stop becoming a pot VR world in a way
gene felt the ECT and the drugs were
actually contributing to her depression
so she began secretly cutting back on
her dosage
against the advice of highlights staff
it was an active rebellion
with positive effect as I gradually cut
down
are gradually got much much better all
these drowsiness depression lack of
interest
the last drugs I were on the mall that
started lifting
the change was amazing without the drugs
I'd almost forgotten
what it felt like to be awake and alive
the
again not want that was love life that
was marvelous jeans resistance to her
psychiatrist's was part of a wider
phenomenon
too many patients doctors nurses and
over-reliant on pills the new tools of
the trade
they saw drugs being used as blunt
instruments
in a way that was out of step with the
spirit at the time on
firms Britain in the sixties was
undergoing enormous social changes
there was a new freedom to break down
barriers
can challenge orthodoxy on the drive to
close the silence captured this
rebellious mood
on mental hospitals were just another
battleground
in a power struggle establishment
there are see a whole raft of civil
libertarian movement to get going
ideas about what mentions really is and
how it should be treated
become ideas to social interest at the
forefront in his radical new thinking
was the controversial psychiatrist are
delaying
his books and speeches outlined a new
approach to treatment
in which the patient not the doctor new
best
they wish I wouldn't word got her true
/param arab girl
are television earned air
to the proper rap and this is exactly
why I think there any American who had
great defense with a nerd
particular repeated acted through his
books and ideas
caused a sensation the general thesis is
a positive experiences
thats we live in a mad world and a
normal response to a mad world is to be
mad
and that the that the sanity that most
has managed to maintain is actually
two more abnormal sort of response but
many powerful mainstream psychiatrists
working in the Asylum's
closed ranks against the new ideas
blanks thinking was treated as
peripheral
meanwhile some doctors were seeking
progress and on experimental lines
particularly in surgery I'm
on and a minute ago slain 10
psychiatrist at high rates so confident
about one pioneer in former
brain operation that they gave
permission for a documentary crew
to film it being carried out on one of
the patients the documentary focused on
mickey Chapman
who'd been admitted to highlight several
times as a patient during the early
seventies
tablet smart our job to turn it in a
time
where meditation top
which is your education a big one
been digitally contact Maggie was a
42-year-old housewife with five children
she was struggling to cope and was prone
to violent al
last chemicals
and he said ok to me added Shaw an
animated
upset me kids saw and just russia now
every just altered trainer this and I
every so often I just she stepped
cool company markets said each
left the hospital highlights on piano
doesn't on
during one of those days it highlights
Maggie was approached about a new
operation
which doctors convinced her could end
her fits a violent
room was telling me now
how Mack 10 public eventually I would
end up doing life in prison term ad
on in a min just prefer less in my life
I was laying down arms
no i buy what do you of us money want
not
Scotstoun and it was telling me how I
bennie thayer
from this operation it was to burnish
pat my brain
it was stopped me
some getting angry and a bit helpless
at been violent night believe you
as you home don't do anything them
you're not going to spend among your
in a mental hospital which will do mom
you know it at the time
spent in a mental hospital has gradually
going to go on increasing
room and you're going to end up and so
it forever balancing the risks
with an operation a games the risks
to the patient did not doing the
impression an important
it was terrifying surgery the doctors
regarded as a huge leap forward
Maggie was taken from his side into the
local hospital
there 29 on balls were fixed in her
forehead
to act as guides for electrodes which
would pinpoint a crucial part of her
brain
the electrode is attached to the
electricity supply
and the current is switched on
stimulating the area
at the bottom of the electric home
have to do more why did you have to do
that mom
from the new shocking
under gooden shouldn't yes crime
I'm pretty sure mmm
nice that made this decision made if a
motorbike
pass me all some Listerine in the world
it's like a hoe
got I just touched down so everything
shakes and had
keep looking I'm burn
you have people thing I don't look up
when he got the response to fit in my
eyes
the pupils right capsized gun
that's when you know that connected the
power
I'm a brain and react to tear a new
electrode is put in the correct position
and to this will be attached a much
larger current
which causes the tip of the electrode to
heat up district say
pro bomb and then peace map right now
maggie's doctors regard to the operation
as a success it could at least get him
out at high rides
but she insists the effects of the
surgery
with debilitating I woulda
is only for five years could communicate
with people when I like
me speech income and the body
me but it was all one-way Mackey is now
successful campaigner for local
community causes
she's adamant that she has put her life
together
in spite of the operation not because it
her experiment treatment is now a piece
of surgical history
maybe still bitterly regrets what was
done to her
and how she was persuaded to consent to
it I don't think I needed that dream
and and I look at it this way right
there's more violence inflicted on me
that I have a
inflicted on anybody that with GBH what
they did to my
bring I'll never forgive and forget
by the mid-70s in a panel had hoped that
many
if not all the old mental institutions
would have disappeared
but not a single asylum claims Britain
had entered a recession
bringing drastic cuts in health spending
members in the silence had to be reduced
at many hospitals the cul happened
gradually one more data timing
up
it started in the early seventies when
award would be shut down
if a person died in that water a patient
with this
Josh in this world with physically
removed the bed so that nobody could be
admitted into it again
if GP's wanted to refer a patient for
possible admission for observation
there wasn't a bed any longer people had
to be missed in the community had to be
cared for in the community
throughout the nineteen seventies almost
every asylum in Britain remained
open but as individual award shut down
many former patients were tipped onto
the streets to cope with life outside
in the early nineteen eighties the BBC's
brass tax program
found it was left to charities like the
Salvation Army
to pick up the pieces the the I
the sixty-five thousand beds in
long-stay wards have been phased out in
20 years
but the community care that was supposed
to take their place
this case the materialized the long-term
mentally ill are still with us
but now in many cases fending for
themselves I'm
comfort you today and every day
mine jumping migrant
and darkness a schizophrenic
and turn I then became revolving-door
patient
cool
telling I hospital in Sussex was home to
Andrew voice in various points in
seventies
well he had had a nervous breakdown when
he was 23 me
and ended up being committed been
discharged several times in well
always never got wise by the oldest on
May showed
they would give me medication by
injection by
founder the talk of the side effect
colder
acuff easier and a I went to be
extremely restless
bonds anticipation the same time
for a week Diane night after the
injection
it was number anybody experienced and
and he was just anxious to avoid the
painful symptoms
is the scion most to me mu
like many others he was a victim in the
diminishing number
the long-stay bed
I would get paranoid I would be living
rough I wouldn't be looking after myself
not been neglecting myself
and I'll get return to use on immunity
by the police
and that was the night you have more
revolving-door life
and 10 got back into this on-again I
would stop in ejections again and
they did this about 12 times between
about 1975 and about 1990
beyond the asylum walls many patients
find it was little organized K
a new hope for secure life
but there was no going back
in the nineteen eighties the signs
finally began to close
revolution in life
swiftly with the momentum the victim
by nineteen ninety 200,000 patients have
been discharged into wider society
history is taking its revenge on the
institutions
the mental hospital is becoming extinct
one after another the great victorian
buildings began a process is shifting
their patients Alma's
into the community and shutting their
gates for ever
incentive doing things piecemeal
and things are old anyone rush it was
you know it
Wakefield and decided to go in today
shack at the hospital's
who dis be lived in the same
Wolverhampton Birmingham no love them
are going to do the same to English
people
with them so everybody went out into the
community this was the start of care in
the community as we know it today
the idea was that the majority of
patients be placed out in the community
with psychiatric support
an ITV film documented the closure have
one mental disability institution
in Stockport under the new system there
would still be heads for some
acute cases but for most patients
it was the start a new life you thank
you very much for your
everything you need to know was still
worth senator
the gym I love champ
who the trickle of people who've been
leaving hospital during the last decade
is now a flood it's a revolution
against institutional care the new rules
mean that everyone has the right to
assay
in their own future well
freedom is government policy
the songs were closed down one missus
thatcher
she's a strange person to thank for an
active social justice
but we have her to thank for around
emancipator yasser
former psychiatric patients by closing
down our silence
with the closure the signs came a new
spirit among patients
as they begin to confront the realities
of life outside
they found a new self-confidence it was
a chance to share
in the individualism at the time no once
you actually stopped
destroying people's lives by looking
them up destroying
any kind individuality you actually did
it in the floodgates
saying hang on this said people in
believe they are actually worth more
than that
omits the wreckage the Asylum's
a grassroots movement sprang up in which
patients challenge doctors preeminent
role in decisions about treatment
the user movement
as it was called campaign successfully
for patients to be more than the passive
recipients
of Psychiatry now we have a system that
people expect to be on want to be
knowledgeable about their problems and
they want to be involved in assaults is
treatments that doctors prescribed
John Tuckwell who was first admitted
into a mental hospital in 1953 because
of her panic attacks
was not released into the outside world
she had been in one asylum or another
for a third of a century
testing were being free free after
to Israel have used should own charm
even their heads aerobatic magnetic
really think that do things for yourself
Jones transition to the outside world
was filmed by her local health service
to show the challenges of caring
community long-term patients had to get
used to like amidst
decades-old Dame routines left behind
the reality wasn't old gym had hoped for
where they put me and it really shake I
had no probs
tables and I I have varying
happy I had that magical ethical can't
I had nothing to for India free I had
their own money
and they're waiting day and this hair
electorate hardly anything
getting there
like many other patients
Joan had to cope the certain amount of
stigma with the show to the silent gone
old prejudices came to the surface who
when I
supa are of battery for which mr. track
they don't forget your window was and
get our share sites
not now she as it was an American
history
sometime people were sent to me
why did you go back to brew law so I a
set of our secure you can never go back
pay
but john has survived
she's made a life for herself in the
community with the help of a camera
and continued medication in another era
she might have remained a long stay
bored in an asylum until she died
like many others jim has found a degree
freedom I filled with the optimism that
certain
there was a future in the community for
people and
term we could set so goals for ourselves
and we could achieve things and
we could begin to take better control
over our lives
but the euphoria was short-lived the
political honeymoon for care in the
community was over very quickly
December 1992 at Finsbury Park tube
station in London
and recently released psychiatric
patient
staff to passenger neon and killed
it was the most notorious have several
disturbing incidents
which Joe to the public's ideas about
the new forms care
it sparked panic in many parts of
society
hymns its 11 a.m. in a North London
police station
officers are being briefed about a
potential killer not by a colleague
but by the man psychiatrist and the
problem over the last three weeks has
been increasing
threats and violence in specific threats
if wanting to kill
variously his probation officer his
girlfriend his mother in 1997 the BBC's
Panorama programme
followed to work as a consultant
psychiatrist in North London
think he is at the moment up
it was a vision of psychiatric services
that nobody involved in care in the
community
wanted to see roundup
both psychiatrist am police judge
overwhelming force
is necessary
releasing thousands have psychiatric
patients into society
raised a whole new set of problems what
seems to happen in the nineties
is that people suddenly start to get
cold feet about it all in and start to
fear that actually what this might mean
is that you call loads loads have
have people with uncontrolled mental
illness running about society causing
mayhem
K the newly elected Labour government
was clearly on the side of safety first
health secretary Frank Dobson openly
declared
community can had failed the political
response was ultimately restrictive
legislation
doctors were given powers to force
patients in the community to take
medication
or risk losing their newfound freedom
too many people
it seems like a step backwards %uh
high Royds was finally closed
in 2003 0 it was one of the last relic
so the asylum network
unlike many others was bought by
developers to be turned into luxury
flats
them
I felt it was passed its best by
it'd damage duty it it's your bitch cars
but a.m. people like the change Haram
fortunate still need to be cared for
this place did indeed provide refuge
from the world for some patients
asylum
in the true sense some feel that this
idea
protection rest has been lost 0
that the community can never replace
this kind
institution lower fee the use the
the new local serb to Community Care
is this also I do think
real music is not on my persian
the water I'm
there even those who think that the
failure the Asylum's has been
exaggerated
I'm
but few people have time for nostalgia
I get very angry when I see people
glorifying the me know these lovelies
states in beautiful victorian buildings
in the country
they will of all places they were
demeaning devaluing places I know
no one who would love to go back to a
forty buddy Doomtree
and that bad and then locker nadine's
Bible and the shared clients
the
on Britain's asylums are now closed
forever
these were once extraordinary places
home to more than 250,000 people
at the height but they had
outlive the ideals of the Victorian
architect and too often had become
dustbins humanity
but leave behind the lives they
transformed
Abdul realize that although I was
in the system five years which seems an
awful in long time
a funnel the patient's five years can
turn into fifty sixty years or whatever
in that sense I can see that I was one
of the lucky ones
the
suppose else feel hungry but I but just
to get me where cat Canon
gonna my life from
I'm beside one in on
feet in anger all the time may I fully
with any word
the Open University has produced a CD
exploring creative responses to mental
health
for your free copy into BBC Doki Doki
UK forward slash hedren will call
0845 366 80
ok